{
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Relation — Slot 2 (10 Questions)",
  "duration": 28,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Relation — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Let L be a set with a relation R which is transitive, anti-symmetric and reflexive and for any two elements  \\(a, b \\in L\\), let the least upper bound \\(lub (a, b)\\) and the greatest lower bound \\(glb (a, b)\\) exist. Which of the following is/are true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L is a poset</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L is a Boolean algebra</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L is a lattice</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L is a poset</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1481/gate1999-2-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The number of binary relations on a set with n elements is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(n^2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^n\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n^2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n^2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1456/gate1999-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The binary relation \\(R = \\{(1, 1), (2, 1), (2, 2), (2, 3), (2, 4), (3, 1), (3, 2), (3, 3), (3, 4)\\}\\) on the set \\(A=\\{1, 2, 3, 4\\}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>reflexive, symmetric and transitive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>neither reflexive, nor irreflexive but transitive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>irreflexive, symmetric and transitive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>irreflexive and antisymmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>neither reflexive, nor irreflexive but transitive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1675/gate1998-2-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(R_1\\) and \\(R_1\\) be two equivalence relations on a set. Consider the following assertions:<br>\nI.  \\(R_1 \\cup R_2\\) is an equivalence relation<br>\nII. \\(R_1 \\cap R_2\\) is an equivalence relation<br>\nWhich of the following is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both assertions are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Assertions (i) is true but assertions (ii) is not true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Assertions (ii) is true but assertions (i) is not true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (i) nor (ii) is true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Assertions (ii) is true but assertions (i) is not true</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1644/gate1998-1-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Suppose A is a finite set with n elements. The number of elements in the largest equivalence relation of A is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(n^2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n+1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(n^2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1643/gate1998-1-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The number of equivalence relations of the set {1,2,3,4} is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>24</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>15</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2259/gate1997-6-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Let R be a non-empty relation on a collection of sets defined by \\(_{A}R_ B\\) if and only if \\(A \\cap B = \\phi\\). Then, (pick the true statement) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A is reflexive and transitive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is symmetric and not transitive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R is not reflexive and not symmetric</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>R is symmetric and not transitive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2731/gate1996-2-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let R be a symmetric and transitive relation on a set A. Then <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R is reflexive and hence an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R is reflexive and hence a partial order</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R is reflexive and hence not an equivalence relation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2606/gate1995-1-19\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The less-than relation, \\(\\lt\\), on reals is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1993)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a partial ordering since it is asymmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a partial ordering since it is antisymmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>not a partial ordering because it is not asymmetric and not reflexive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>not a partial ordering because it is not antisymmetric and reflexive</p>",
            "<b>E.</b> <p>none of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>E.</b> <p>none of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2303/gate1993-8-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following relations:<pre><code>  \nR1(a,b) iff (a+b) is even over the set of integers\nR2(a,b) iff (a+b) is odd over the set of integers\nR3(a,b) iff a.b &gt; 0 over the set of non-zero rational numbers\nR4(a,b) iff |a - b| &lt;= 2 over the set of natural numbers\n </code></pre>\nWhich of the following statements is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R1 and R2 are equivalence relations, R3 and R4 are not</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R1 and R3 are equivalence relations, R2 and R4 are not</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R1 and R4 are equivalence relations, R2 and R3 are not</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R1, R2, R3 and R4 are all equivalence relations</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>R1 and R3 are equivalence relations, R2 and R4 are not</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/695/gate2001-1-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}